Paul James Wright

CONTACT INFORMATION Rm 614, Kelvin Building University of Glasgow Glasgow, G12 8QQ United Kingdom Work: +44 (0)14133 08855 Web: www.pauljwright.co.uk Email: paul.wright@glasgow.ac.uk Publication List: SAO/NASA ADS

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My interests range from stellar to solar physics; my main interests lie in the heating of the solar atmosphere, including active regions and loops. I have expertise in the analysis of spectroscopic and narrowband Extreme Ultra-Violet (EUV) and X-ray data from the *Solar Dynamics Observatory* and *Hinode*, in addition to the hard X-ray (HXR) observations from *NuSTAR*'s heliophysics campaign. I am currently using a hydrodynamics code (Enthalpy-Based Thermal Evolution of Loop, EBTEL) to model light curves from coronal loops. I am particularly interested in the weak bremsstrahlung emission, with a view to understanding the requirements for future X-ray instrumentation to study the coronal heating problem.

EDUCATION

University of Glasgow, Glasgow, UK

2014 - April 2018

Ph.D. Solar Physics

Thesis Topic: *The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings* Advisers: Dr Iain G. Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

University of Southampton, Southampton, UK

2010 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

First-class honours (1:1)

Adviser: Professor Malcolm Coe

Harvard University/Harvard-Smithsonian CfA, Cambridge, MA, USA

2013 - 2014

MPhys Astrophysics with a year abroad

Thesis Topic: *Superflare Rates of Solar-Like Stars* Advisers: Dr Steven H. Saar, Dr Jeremy J. Drake

CURRENT ACADEMIC APPOINTMENT

Affiliate Staff Member, University of Glasgow

2017 – present

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

• Using the EBTEL hydrodynamics code to model light curves from coronal loops. The parameter space of these simulations will be constrained by observations obtained during the *NuSTAR* heliophysics campaign, and these simulations will used to test a variety of analysis techniques.

PREVIOUS ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS

Post-Graduate Research Assistant, University of Glasgow

2014 - 2017

SUPA School of Physics and Astronomy

Project: The Energetics of Small Flares and Brightenings

- Analysed observations of the Sun with *NuSTAR*, a telescope not designed for heliophysics. These observations are the most sensitive of their kind and have resulted in numerous, wide-ranging, highly-collaborative peer-reviewed publications.
- Analysed non-flaring coronal time-series in pursuit of signatures of the coronal heating mechanism. Techniques included time-lag analysis (cross-correlation), Fourier analysis, wavelet analysis, and local intermittency measure (LIM).
- Studied the temperature distribution of the solar atmosphere through the recovery of an ill-posed inverse problem (the differential emission measure, DEM) using techniques such as Tikhonov regularisation, Markov-chain Monte Carlo, and sparsity.
- The press-release image produced from the *NuSTAR* observations obtained for Wright *et al.* 2017 was published by numerous news outlets, and is one of the five iconic images from *NuSTAR*'s first five years in space.

Collaborators: Dr Iain Hannah, Dr Alexander MacKinnon

PREVIOUS ACADEMIC APPOINTMENTS (CONT.)	Visiting Researcher, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (GSFC) Heliophysics Science Division	2016	
	 Explored the possibility of implementing DEM maps in the Helioviewer project, and their usefulness as an input for various established analysis techniques. Collaborators: <i>Dr Nicholeen Viall, Dr Jack Ireland</i> 		
	Research Scholar , Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics (CfA) Solar and Stellar X-Ray Group	2013 – 2014	
	 Designed and implemented a sophisticated stellar flare detection routine for long-cadence (30 mins) <i>Kepler</i> data obtained from a proprietary set of spectroscopically verified solar-type stars in three open clusters. A preliminary version of this work had coverage by Science, and The Smithsonian Mag- 		
	azine.	_	
	Collaborators: Dr Steven Saar, Dr Søren Meibom, Dr Jeremy Drake, Dr Vin		
	Summer Research Intern, University of Southampton Astronomy Group	2013	
	 Investigated the presence of double blue straggler sequences in globul. Hubble Space Telescope (ACS, WFPC2) data. Collaborators: <i>Dr Andrea Dieball</i> 	ar clusters using	
REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS	[1] Marsh, A. J., Smith, D. M., Glesener, L. et al 2017. First NuSTAR Limits on Quiet Sun Hard X-Ray Transient Events, ApJ, 849, 131		
	[2] Wang, J., Simões, P. J. A., Jeffrey, N. L. S. et al 2017. Observations of Reconnection Flows in a Flare on The Solar Disk, ApJL, 847, L1		
	[3] Wright, P. J. , Hannah, I. G., Grefenstette, B. W., et al 2017. Microflare Heating of a Solar Active Region Observed with NuSTAR, Hinode/XRT, and SDO/AIA, ApJ, 844, 132		
	[4] Kuhar, M., Krucker, S., Hannah, I. G., et al 2017. Evidence of Significant Energy Input in the Late Phase of a Solar Flare from NuSTAR X-ray Observations, ApJ, 835, 6		
FIRST AUTHOR	[5] Wright, P. J., Hannah, I. G., Viall, N. M., et al		
PUBLICATIONS IN PREPARATION	[6] Wright, P. J., Saar, S. H., Meibom, S., et al		
Conferences,	Invited Oral Presentations		
WORKSHOPS, &	ISSI Team Meeting: Coronal Nanoflares, Bern, CH	2016	
SCHOOLS	Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics, Cambridge, MA, USA	2014	
	Oral/ePoster Presentations Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII, Palermo, Sicily, IT	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Hinode 10, Nagoya, JP	2016	
	National Astronomy Meeting 2016, Nottingham, UK	2016	
	Hinode 9, Belfast, UK Glasgow-Cambridge Flare Workshop, Glasgow, UK	2015 2015	
	Poster Presentations		
	European Solar Physics Meeting (ESPM), Budapest, HU	2017	
	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS), Portland, OR, USA	2017	
	Living with a Star (SDO/LWS) Workshop, Burlington, VT, USA	2016	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VII, Cambridge, UK	2015 2015	
	National Astronomy Meeting (NAM) 2015, Llandudno, UK	2015	

223rd AAS Meeting, National Harbor, MD, USA

2014

Paul James Wright

Conferences,	Schools Attended		
Workshops, &	CESRA Radio Summer School 2015, Glasgow, UK	2015	
SCHOOLS (CONT.)	STFC Advanced Summer School in Solar Physics, Dundee, UK	2014	
	Conferences/Workshops Attended		
	NuSTAR Heliophysics Workshop (remote participation), Berkeley, CA, USA	2017	
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2015	
	Royal Astronomical Society Discussion Meeting: Results from IRIS, London, U		
	SUPA Cormack Astronomy Meeting, Edinburgh, UK	2014 2014	
	1st Space Glasgow Research Conference, Glasgow, UK	2014	
AWARDS AND	University of Glasgow		
GRANTS	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Student Poster Award	2017	
TOTAL: £7000	Solar Physics Division Meeting (SPD/AAS) Studentship Award	2017	
	Coronal Loops Workshop VIII Travel Award	2017	
	National Astronomical Observatory of Japan Travel Award	2016	
	Hinode 9 Travel Award	2015	
	European Space Agency/Cambridge Philosophical Society Travel Award	2015	
	University of Southampton	2012	
	Research Scholarship	2013 2013	
	Summer Studentship Grant	2013	
TEACHING	Coursera Inc.		
	•	017 – present	
	An invited mentor of a course in the Data Science specialisation offered by Jo University.	шіѕ поркінѕ	
	University of Glasgow		
	Astronomy 1 Tutorial Demonstrator	2016 - 2017	
	Supervised students, and marked first-year astronomy problem sets.		
	Astronomy 3/4 (Honours) Laboratory Demonstrator	2015 - 2016	
	Demonstrated, supervised, and marked a number of final-year research projects covering		
	topics such as asteroid light curves, and solar limb darkening.		
	Physics Pre-University Summer School	2015	
	Taught at a pre-university school for students entering first year.		
MEMBERSHIPS	NuSTAR Heliophysics Working Group, Member 20	015 – present	
		015 – present	
	Member of Paola Testa's ISSI Team: New Diagnostics of Particle Accelera		
	Coronal Nanoflares from Chromospheric Observations and Modelling		
	Royal Astronomical Society, RAS Fellow 20	014 – present	
COMMUNITY	Nature Communications, Reviewer 20	017 – present	
INVOLVEMENT	Glasgow Astronomy & Astrophysics Group Meeting, Organiser	2017 – present	
INVOLVENIENT	CESRA Radio Summer School, Volunteer Organiser	2015	
a		***	
SCIENTIFIC OUTREACH	Glasgow Science Centre, Demonstrator	2016	
	British Science Week, Demonstrator	2016	
	Institute of Physics: Women and Girls in Science, Demonstrator	2016	
	Scottish Television (STV), Guest Presenter World Wide Telescope, Ambassador	2015	
	World Wide Telescope, Ambassador	2013 - 2014	

Paul James Wright

SCIENTIFIC	BBC Stargazing Live, Demonstrator	2013		
OUTREACH	So'ton Astrodome, Demonstrator	2012		
(CONT.)	BBC Bang Goes The Theory Roadshow, Demonstrator	2012		
	UK Solar Physics (UKSP) Nuggets , concise, easy-to-read science articles 84. The first <i>NuSTAR</i> microflare	2017		
	Hinode/XRT Picture of the Week (XPOW)			
	The First Microflare Observations with <i>Hinode/XRT & NuSTAR</i>	2017		
PERSONAL PROJECTS	ColourBlind, A repository for colour-blind-friendly colour tables.			
PROFESSIONAL	ONAL Coursera, Inc. (MOOC Platform)			
DEVELOPMENT	Using Coursera.org, a massive open online course (MOOC) platform, to take specialisation (a series of related courses and a final capstone project) offered by accredited universities to further develop skills and understanding in a wide range of computer science topics.			
	Data Science, Johns Hopkins University	2017 – present		
	Nine-course (plus capstone) introduction to data science.			
	Mastering Software Development in R, Johns Hopkins University	2017 – present		
	Four-course (plus capstone) specialisation providing riguourous training	in R.		
	Statistics with R, Duke University	2017 – present		
	Four-course (plus capstone) specialisation providing further training in F on statistics.	R, with emphasis		

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

Computing: IDL, Python, R, Bash, ETEX, IRAF, git, GitHub, Microsoft Office, Adobe Creative Cloud, Linux/Unix, Mac OSX, Microsoft Windows,

General: Data Analysis, Data Visualisation, Interdisciplinary Collaboration, Public Speaking, Statistics, Teaching, Writing (Technical & Lay)